All right.
Since there is no bell, you don't know that it's time.
That's the function of a bell.
Ivan Paulo figured that out more than a century ago with dogs.
Do you guys know about that reinforcement learning principles?
He fed the dogs after a bell, and dogs started expecting food to come after a bell.
In the past in this lecture room, there was a bell that used to ring after when the class was
supposed to start and everybody expected to expected the class to start when the bell rang.
So we're all the reinforcement learning agents as you can see, right?
That's true.
And there are some psychologists who believe that we're only reinforcement learning agents, like BF
Skinner, who was a very prominent psychologist.
These are behavioural psychologists.
It's a bit hard to sustain that probably, but it's good to think about it anyway, especially in this
time when people are trying to make machines learn things.
It's not clear what kind of models that humans follow to learn, but reinforcement learning is
certainly one of them.
And reinforcement learning is very different from what people are doing with LLMS today.
Reinforcement learning could be a part of it, but LLMS are more based on Transformers, neural
networks, etcetera.
So it's good to think about it anyway.
This, it just reminded me.
Digression came because of the bell, as you can see, right?
But computing principles are very much related to life principles that we follow, especially today.
OK.
You're here not for machine learning lecture, which I'm incapable of delivering anyway because
that's not my expertise.
You can take someone else's class for that.
You're here for digital design and computer architecture, right?
I'm not sure.
OK, Some people say yes, who's not here for digital design and computer architecture?
I don't see any hands.
So that's good.
You can go out if you don't have to stay here, you know.
But I mean, you can also listen and maybe you'll get excited, who knows?
Because this is an area of investigation, a topic in computing that I believe is going to be even
more exciting and even more important going into the future because some areas of computing are
relatively easier to offload to machines in my opinion.
And as we are seeing also in systems like programming debugging you can of course.
Offload more and more to machines and machines will get better and better at that.
But it's not clear if this area is going to be as easy to offload, especially when we try to
manufacture very advanced semiconductor technologies and we when we try to come up different with
different principles of execution.
So that's what we're going to talk about in this lecture.
We're going to learn how computers really work from the ground up.
This is not a programming course, although you will do some programming of real hardware and you
will learn how how computer is, how a computer is built from the ground up.
Does that sound good?
OK, and we'll discuss why that is important later as well in this lecture.
So this lecture is really an introductory lecture to discuss essentially what computer architecture
is about.
And we will at the very end hopefully start with transistor as a building block.
Essentially all computers you have are made of what is called Metaloc side semiconductor transistors
and usually it's with complementary Metaloc side semiconductor transistors, CMOS.
You will hopefully see that by the end of today, tomorrow and essentially A transistor we're going
to, we're going to treat that the circuit or this device, we're going to treat that as an
abstraction for digital logic.
We're going to keep it open or closed, like this wall switch over there.
I don't want to turn off the lights, but if I press one of those lights, it'll turn off the light,
right?
Essentially, we'll treat transistors, a wall switch, and build circuits on top of that.
Does that sound good?
So we'll demystify all of the magic, all of this abstraction that you have in software, LLMS,
etcetera, are running on these things called transistors that are connected together to form
certain functions, in particular, for example, addition, multiplication, memory access.
And we're going to see all of those and demystify all of those during the course of this lecture.
We're going to actually see how existing GPUs are built in Lecture 20 or so or maybe earlier, how
existing machine learning exercises are built, 5 existing CPUs are built.
Does that sound good?
OK.
And some of these things that we are going to discuss are going to be quite interesting, quite
advanced, but we'll build up to it.
Basically, we'll, we'll not leave off any level that will hopefully be unclear.
If there's something unclear, please write to us.
Please ask questions.
We encourage that a lot.
OK, With that said, let's get into some of the material over here.
I have a lot of slides, but I'm going to skip some of them.
So all these are introduction to us.
I see some people over here who are part of my teaching team.
So who am I?
I'm a professor at ETH.
I've been here 10 years now, too long, longer than anywhere else I've been in my life, basically.
And I before this, I was at Carnegie Mellon University as a professor, and before that I was at
Microsoft Research.
And I found that the Computer Architecture research group at Microsoft Research, which did a lot of
exciting things over the course of many years.
Before that, I was a PhD student at the University of Texas at Austin.
What does that sound?
OK, it's gone, not from me.
And I did my PhD in computer architecture, and we're going to see some of those topics in Lecture 24
or so when we talk about prefetching.
Prefetching is the idea of a processor, a microprocessor, hardware, predicting what you're going to
access next and getting that data early to the processor.
This will become all clear later on.
And before that, I was a bachelor student like you guys at the University of Michigan, where I
studied computer engineering and psychology.
I did a lot of stints at industry.
I spent a lot of time at Intel, AMD, building their microprocessors, doing research on them.
Some of the prefetching ideas that may be employed on some of the computers may be inside there in
the things that you're using.
I spent a lot of time at Google VM Ware and of course Microsoft Research, right, and Stanford for my
sabbatical.
So if you have questions about industry, we're going to cover a lot of industry relevant things also
here.
A lot of the things that we're going to cover are what really drives computing hardware today.
But computing software is always built on computing hardware.
So the AI evolution is enabled today because of the computing hardware that we're going to study.
So I work on computer architecture, computing systems.
I have very broad interests, hardware, security, bioinformatics.
I'm not going to bore you with all of these things because we're going to talk about some of these
things.
Let me introduce some other people over here.
Mohammed, who's sitting over there is my Co instructor.
He is part of my group.
He's been with us for 9 plus years, right, for both visiting and then more recently a senior
researcher and lecturer.
He's got his degrees from the top school at Iran.
Sheriff, University of Technology, and he's done a lot of outstanding research in computer
architecture.
People from University of Tehran may contest that and that's fine.
OK, you can talk to him.
He's going to deliver a bunch of lectures.
Also, he's the Co instructor and our head teaching assistant is over there, Konstantina.
She's also a senior lecturer and researcher in my group, and she's got her PhD from the top school
at Greece, although some people may contest that, including some people sitting close to her
perhaps.
And she's been with us for two years, right?
And she works, she does research on hardware, software, code design also.
So if you have a lot of questions on assignments, Constantina is the person to ask.
Be nice.
She's very nice.
OK.
And Jihang, who is not here right now, is our other head teaching assistant.
He joined my group recently from Tsinghua, which is a top school in China.
Is Jihang here?
I think he's in China right now, so.
OK.
Yeah.
So if you have questions, you can e-mail right now.
OK.
And then labs.
We have labs in this course.
How many people are aware that we have labs?
OK, that's good.
People are paying attention.
And Ottabach, who is over there smiling, is our senior, well, teaching Ed, teaching assistant.
He's a pH senior PhD student in my group.
He's going to graduate soon, so I get the best of him before he graduates.
And he's been doing a lot of work on computer architecture.
So you can talk to these people about their research also because they're doing a lot of impactful
research.
And finally, last but not least, Mayank is in the back over there in purple.
It's easier to find.
He's also a head teaching assistant.
He's recently joined my group.
He's he's one of the younger PhD students and he's doing a lot of work on homomorphic encryption,
privacy preserving technologies and how to accelerate them and how to make them better.
So you can see that we touch a lot of topics in the group.
And computer architecture and digital design actually touches a lot of these topics.
How do you compute on encrypted data is a fascinating area that Mayank is working on, for example.
OK, does that sound good?
Now you know whom to contact, At least the major people.
I'm going to introduce some of the other people later on because we have a large group of teaching
assistants, student assistants, student assistants, students who have taken this course in the past
and they've enjoyed it so much that they want to actually help future generations like you.
So those are actually the people who have gone through the course, some of them multiple times.
Maria, for example, over here is one of them, but you will see some of them over time as well.
OK, so this is my research group.
I'm going to skip some of these slides.
If you want to learn more about us, there's a lot of information online or ask people over here.
We put put out newsletters.
You can see how a research group operates if you're interested in that at some point in the future,
maybe.
So we held one of our conferences recently, and this is our newsletter recently.
We have a lot of material online.
Again, I'm not going to bore you with this.
We are very proud of our PhD and postdoc alumni.
Are they here?
Any of them?
They will come.
Some of them are travelling for conferences.
So we have 25 alumni and PhD and they are all decorated with a lot of awards.
Well deserved.
And we have a lot of computing future interviews.
So if you're interested in the future of computing, you can find a lot of materials.
These are actually some recent interviews that I did with IEEE Computer Society, and I'm going to
talk about some of these later in later lectures.
Actually, today we're going to talk about processing in memory.
Very little bit to discuss what's happening today in computing.
OK.
If you're interested in suggestions, I have a lot of them.
You can watch them or ask me.
OK, So what do we do?
As I said, our core focusing is to enable fundamentally better computers.
And it's that's the core of digital design, actually digital design and computer architecture.
What is the goal of what we're doing?
Enable a computing device that can do something better, right.
If you're going to do something worse than before, there is not much point in it.
Maybe you can make money, but you're not advancing the state-of-the-art.
Our goal is really to advance state-of-the-art, so come up with new ways of designing computers.
So that's going to be the focus of this course, this mindset of growth or enabling, doing something
fundamentally better.
So there was, for example, in 1980s, how many people are as old as 1980s here?
I guess I may be the only one.
OK, some of them.
That's good.
Yeah.
We don't discriminate on age.
You can learn at any age.
In fact, some people have formed Some of the most powerful companies did that after.
After, after they were 65 years old, People retire here when they're 65 years old.
Anyway, that's a joke, kind of.
OK, so basically in 1980s when people were designing the MIPS architecture, MIPS computers that
you're going to actually do some studies on MIPS and I'm going to ask what that means later on.
Not today you can think about it, but the MIPS architecture, the people designed the MIPS R2000 and
you're going to you're going to actually design something very similar to what MIPS R 2000 is in
your labs.
Well, in, in, in also the lectures.
And this was an in order processor, very simple, a few stages pipelined and people said this is the
best computing machine.
We should not design anything higher performance than this because nobody needs it.
This was actually said.
People say it, In fact, engineers say it sometimes.
And this is a terrible mindset because if we actually stop there, then we wouldn't be having
anything, any of the technology that we have today.
So this course would stop at lecture.
I don't know, 10 maybe.
Do you agree?
But we're going to go to lecture 26 and we're going to enable new things because we're going to
actually always push for doing better.
And doing better is really the enabling function of innovation, research, development.
Once you do something better, then somebody else wants to do something better also.
That's how you actually design better systems in general.
Of course, better in different many aspects, right?
Then the question becomes what is better, right?
There are many metrics and we're going to talk about that also in this course.
Performance is 1 metric.
Energy is very important metric.
We're going to talk about that robustness.
How do you design a system that is actually very robust.
Robustness has a lot of aspects, secure, private, safe, reliable, available.
All of these are predictable.
All of these are aspects of robustness that are really important.
When we are going to cover some of these in this course, a lot of our focus will be performance.
Cost will be another metric, ease of use will be another metric.
So there will be a lot of metrics.
So this is not, these are not things that we do research on, but these are things that are actually
at the core of this course.
That's why I think this fundamental course at freshman level course is very exciting to teach
because it really cuts to the core concepts of how you actually enable a computer.
Because if you, for example, if your hardware is not robust whenever you do computation, the
computation is wrong.
Sometimes, maybe not always, let's say 95% it's correct, 5% wrong.
How do you design software for it?
It's good to think about it, right?
5% of the time you're going to get wrong results.
Maybe one idea could be to not design that hardware that sounds good.
Or if you design that hardware, how do you fix the problem right?
If the hardware tells you that the computation is wrong, maybe you repeat the computation that
sounds good.
You design hardware that tells you when it's wrong.
That's a very good principle of robust system design.
If you cannot design hardware that's always correct, at least design something that tells you when
it's wrong.
This is called fail fast, meaning it tells you that it's wrong or it fails and doesn't give you
result.
The worst thing, well, maybe not the worst thing, but one of the worst things that can happen is the
hardware computes something incorrectly and you assume that it's correct, but the result is
actually not correct.
And you written software assuming that it's correct, right?
So how do you fix that?
Well, you can play the probability game assuming the hardware is not nice, meaning it doesn't tell
you that's not correct.
You can say, OK, I'm going to execute the same program 10 times and I'm going to vote among them.
So this is actually done.
Also, that's called redundant execution.
You redundantly execute the same program many times and take the most popular result.
Sounds good, right?
Maybe you reduce the probability of incorrect result, but you don't eliminate it completely.
You can start playing the probability game and execute the same program a million times and
hopefully you'll get the result correct.
But again, there's always a probability that you may not be correct, right?
So it's good to think about these design decisions and what we do in this course is that really at
the core of how we design this sort of systems.
I was going to say something about that a million times.
So a million times you execute the same program, Let's assume that you're querying your LLM and you
do it a million times as opposed to once because you you're not sure if it's going to the hardware
that's executing the LLM inference, large language model inference.
Is that actually going to get it correct?
Now you're expanding a lot of energy, right?
These things are actually consuming a lot of energy to begin with, as we will see, and for
redundancy, for redundancy, for robust execution to get the correct result, you're expanding even
more energy.
So the design choices that you make in hardware critically affect what happens to what we really
care about energy and energy directly impacts sustainability, and sustainability all of us should
really care about, even if these huge companies don't care about them and pay lip service to them,
you guys should care about because you guys are the future.
Those old people who are dominating the world are not the future, they're the past and they're going
to be the past.
You guys should really take care of it and really enable the design of much more energy efficient,
high performance and also sustainable systems.
The sustainability was not a component of computing design until recently when we actually started
building very large scale systems, partly due to machine learning and AI.
And this has actually become very dangerous in my opinion, because we're really building systems
that are tapping into the resources of the world in a very intensive way.
And as a result, we may be actually destroying the world more than we should with computers.
So if you think about it, we're our goal is to really design something that enable a better, enables
a better future, but it should not destroy that future also.
OK, so I digress, but this is actually the, the perfect time to discuss these introductory materials
because we're going to see a lot of designs.
It's good to think about what is the performance of the design?
What is the cost of the design?
What is the energy of the design?
What is the sustainability impact?
I'm not going to tell you exactly what that is because that's actually still a research topic.
How do you actually quantify the sustainability cost of a machine?
For example, partly how much hardware goes into the machine.
Bigger hardware is actually in general not nice for sustainability.
Partly what kind of materials go into the machine.
Expensive or scarce materials that require a lot of impact on the world are not good.
Partly how much energy is needed to power up the machine.
How much energy does the machine consume?
Partly how much power is needed to power up the machine, like total design power.
So there are a lot of metrics that actually combine to design a system.
And hopefully what you will get out of this course is to really try to tease out the complexity that
goes into these decisions because there's not only one metric, unfortunately, sometimes there's one
metric.
Like if you design a high performance supercomputer, people say, OK, the only thing I care about is
performance.
Unfortunately, that's not true.
If you look at supercomputers today, it's also energy, it's also cost.
It's also whether you can power this thing.
So even in domains where traditionally people have considered performance is the biggest metric,
that performance is not necessarily the biggest metric.
Energy and other metrics are becoming much more important.
So that's why when we design computers, we should think about different metrics.
And when we design computers, there are a lot of components also.
We're going to cover some of these in this lecture.
I'm not going to go through them right now, but this is what we do in our research as well.
OK, I, I use that slide to talk about a lot of things as you can see.
OK, so these are some of the research topics that we do in my group.
You will, you will get exposed to some of these in later lectures, especially auto design.
Fundamentally robust, secure, reliable, safe, available, predictable architectures, fundamentally
energy efficient architectures, low latency and predictable architecture.
That's important.
And we also look a lot, about a lot into intelligent architectures that can self learn.
Basically, you design some hardware.
It's not static.
So if you look at this hardware, for example, there are some decisions that are made in this
hardware that are dictated by humans.
Humans taught something.
They built the hardware.
And the hardware that's actually almost six years old, the six year old hardware is doing the same
thing every nanosecond for all of its lifetime.
It didn't learn anything.
It's kind of dumb, pretty dumb actually.
In most decisions there is no learning.
You put it in some environment, it it doesn't learn.
Basically it doesn't understand.
It's not self aware.
Even so, our goal is to design systems that are actually much more data-driven.
They can interact with the environment and they can learn and they can do better.
Over time they get better.
Actually.
In fact, this hardware gets worse over time because it ages.
Can we get better with experience, basically?
That's actually very important.
And we're going to see some small pieces of how this is done in microprocessors today when we cover
the topic of branch prediction.
But there's a lot more to be done in this area.
And then there's a lot of architecture designed for important applications like machine learning,
genomics, medicine, and health that we do that.
I will at some point talk about how many people have seen this picture in a prior course.
OK, Where did you see it?
Maybe someone?
Yes.
Where did you see it?
Sorry to pick on you, but a course or?
Yeah, And And a course in another university.
OK, another university.
How many people have seen this picture in this university?
OK, Which course?
This one.
OK, this course.
OK, Thank you.
I'll come back.
So basically this is the transformation hierarchy.
We're going to look at this a lot.
I'm going to actually introduce this a little bit more later on.
We have problems to solve and humans are always have problems.
Humans are great problem generators.
Sometimes useful problems like understanding intelligence, understanding the fundamentals of
science, physics, etcetera, how we nature operates, those are useful problems.
Sometimes they're human generated problems like congestion, right, or sustainable tissues, for
example, that we are talking about.
You have some problems to solve and you need to actually communicate it to the electrons.
In the technologies that we built.
Unfortunately we don't yet speak the electron language.
How many people speak the electron language here?
Not yet.
If you're speaking it, let me know.
I have a start up idea for you.
I am hoping that this will change with more and more intelligent learning.
Maybe we can actually get to speak that language at some point, but that requires a lot of many
years probably.
So as a result, people have developed this hierarchy to communicate with the electrons, and we're
going to see how those electrons work toward the end of this lecture.
If I keep digressing, we're not going to reach that, but let's see.
Hopefully you're having fun.
At least with the electrons.
We build devices, logic, micro architecture, that's the hardware.
And then we have some interface to it.
And with the problem, we, we transform the problem into an algorithm, right, In a programming
language executed on some system software which interacts with the hardware.
So this is the transformation hierarchy, and in this course we're going to especially focus on these
two, although we'll actually focus on logic also.
This is the computer architecture narrow view today because these difficulties in design are not
easy to solve just by thinking about the hardware or the computer architecture in this narrow
manner.
A lot of people are looking at Co designing or designing entire systems, building algorithms for
devices.
So you see a lot of companies for example or researchers both looking into computer architecture as
a more in a more holistic way.
How can we how can I design the entire stack so that I can solve my problem in a better way?
You see this a lot in machine learning systems for example.
People are not saying how can I design the best processor That's good.
I want to design the best processor, but also I want to adapt my software to the best processor so
that I can execute this machine learning application in a fast way.
You can maybe specialized that application to some health.
For example, you, you want to do AI for medicine and a particular area of medicine.
Even you can design systems that are actually much more specialized that way.
So it's good to think about it this way.
And I'm going to give you some examples of this.
So this is called cross layer design and the goal is to achieve the highest metric.
Metric can be efficiency, performance, robustness, security.
And we should really take the expanded view of computer architecture and Co design across the
hierarchy algorithms to devices.
And this is kind of the research approach we're taking in my group.
And you'll see some examples of this that this that's already happening in industry as well.
OK, It's another principle that is really important to me.
Actually, that's why I teach the I love teaching the freshman course because I believe teaching and
research are two sides of the same coin.
What does this mean?
Research is discovering something that no one has discovered before.
That's the ideal research.
You discover something, you invent something, no one has thought of it before.
It's innovative novel.
And teaching is basically teaching that to everyone else.
You basically discovered something and you educate everyone else.
Teaching in a more broader form is education or telling, telling other people what anyone can know,
researchers finding something what that no one found before.
But once you've found something you educate, it becomes a domain of teaching makes sense.
And this becomes an endless loop.
This is my unfortunate animation and it should be a loop actually that way.
So if it's an endless loop, and So what was research 10 years ago is teaching material for me today.
Somebody discovered something like systolic arrays, for example.
That was 50 years ago.
Actually, it's what I did for my PhD.
My PhD thesis was research that no one did before.
But now it's teaching.
I can teach it because anyone can teach it.
Actually, it's no.
So that's why we care a lot about both teaching and.
Research and I think if you actually take the right mindset, you can turn teaching into research
also because you question everything and we're going to question everything in this course.
So these are our courses.
This the website is updated so you can actually go and find spring 2026 and fall 2025 lectures.
Also, we have a bunch of courses.
You can find them on YouTube also.
Probably there are some people who are watching us on YouTube.
You can also watch us on YouTube if you want to drink your beer and watch a lecture.
Probably you cannot do that here.
OK, so this is just to give you a more broader perspective.
This is the digital design and computer architecture course.
We have the older editions online also.
I'm going to talk about them if you're interested in learning more later.
We also have a fundamental of computer architecture course which I don't recommend taking.
If you actually take digital design and computer Architecture, I would recommend taking the advanced
Computer Architecture directly.
This is really a course for electrical engineering students, ECE students, electrical and computer
engineering students.
I would say Advanced Computer Architecture delves into more topics and we have a seminar also which
a lot of students take if they're interested in the topics in this course.
OK, this is just to give you the lay of land.
These are these are links to last year's materials.
You will see that we're going to follow a very similar structure.
Course materials like lectures will slightly change, like the stories I tell will change probably,
although some of them also will remain the same because some of them are very fundamental.
But if you're interested in knowing what will come ahead, you can look at last year's materials.
Does that sound good?
Predictability is good, but we always keep improving the slides.
So this year's slides may contain more up to date information because things are changing quickly in
this field.
Fundamentals remain the same though.
OK, let me go a little bit into what do you want in this course.
Basically, as I said, we we're going to learn how computers work from the ground up.
This is a computing system that may be in your pocket.
This is called a system on a chip SoC and in the middle you have chiplets.
It's actually called the compute chip.
It has a lot of computation capability and a lot of caches.
You will learn about caches later.
And then there's data storage, main memory, and then there's even non volatile data storage like
flash memory.
And then there are sensors.
So we will study how something like this works.
And we're going to start with the compute engine.
Actually, we're going to start with digital design, how to actually build basic blocks, basic
components.
And then later in the course we're going to talk a lot about memory memories because memory is
actually one of the biggest components of today.
You may have realised that memory prices are rising for a good reason, because memory is really
important component of systems.
So what are the high level goals?
Basically, we're going to understand the basics.
That's why we start with the basic components like transistors, and we're going to understand the
principles of design, how to build much more complex systems from very basic components.
And we're going to also understand precedence, meaning what came before, what people did, right.
And we're going to actually do a lot of what people did.
But while studying that, it's also good to question what people didn't.
And this is what I would like to instill in this course.
And you may not be very used to it because once you go through a middle school, high school,
etcetera, you're always given what people did, what people did, what people did.
But it's good to also think about what people didn't do.
Because what people didn't do is what is going to be the biggest innovation that may come, right?
And you guys are all capable of thinking critically and figuring out what can you do better, right?
OK, so based on such understanding, we're going to learn how the modern computer works, actually how
multiple different modern computers work.
We're going to learn how to evaluate trade-offs of different designs and ideas.
This is going to be really important in the lab.
We're going to implement a principle design.
It's very simple microprocessor.
Unfortunately, our time doesn't allow us to do more.
This course is already actually pretty intense, I would say, in terms of the coverage of material.
But labs cannot be that intense because you need to actually debug things.
Although with LLMS today you can do a lot more, I think, right.
Can you do the labs in one day?
Yeah.
OK.
The head TA says one day, yes, but I wouldn't recommend doing that with LLMS, Ben, you won't
understand it and we're going to ask you questions about it.
So don't do it with LLMS, OK.
And you're going to learn to systematically debug increasingly complex systems and hopefully we will
enable you to develop novel out-of-the-box designs.
That's the part what people didn't do.
And the focus is really on basics, precedence principles and how to use them to create and implement
good designs.
So I, I cover a lot of basics, but I also give a lot of examples from existing like state-of-the-art
implementations.
And we're going to talk about that.
So why do you?
Why are you here?
I would say because you're here for a computer science degree and computer science degrees are
important, and this course is actually even more important going into the future because as I said
earlier, it's very hard to replace this course with programming LLM, let's say, although maybe the
labs can be replaced, although that's a very simple lab, a very complex microprocessor design is
going to be very hard to replace.
So you want to know how a computer works if you want a computer science degree, At least that's my
contention.
You may disagree and more importantly maybe regards of your future direction.
Learning the principles that we cover in this course could be useful to design better hardware if
that's what you want to do.
If you know the hardware, you can do better software and better Co design, better system design,
which we really need in systems today.
It can enable you to make better trade-offs in design, whatever you design, in my opinion.
I gave you some example early on, but there are a lot of examples in life.
But you're designing something, and if you actually have designed a computer, the fact that you
designed a computer helps you design that something in a better way and of course, hopefully
understand why computers behave the way they do.
If you're lucky, you will understand some of this.
Sometimes you may not be able to understand because of the complexity of the stack.
Hopefully this will enable you to solve problems better.
These are more general skills, right?
Think in parallel.
Especially doing hardware programming enables you to think in parallel.
That's why using LLMS to actually do your design is not very good because that doesn't enable you to
think in parallel.
Whereas if you go and design the hardware, you will actually need to think about many signals that
are happening at the same time and that enables you to think in parallel.
Whereas LLM is like a human, well, I'm not going to make any more analogy than that, but it's very
serial interaction with all that, right?
And think critically.
So these are the most important things actually, I, I hope you will get out of this course.
So what are the components that we have?
Clearly we have lectures.
Lectures are good for understanding concepts, stories, maybe trade-offs.
So I can convey my experience to you much better through lectures and you will not find a lot of the
experience conveyance in the readings.
Readings are good for reinforcing and going deeper.
We have very good books, but they don't really tell a whole lot of stories about trade-offs as much.
We have homeworks and we're going to do those homeworks in some of the sessions.
We have labs, we have exam test of understanding.
We're going to talk more about that and we'll have some extra credit assignments.
And I don't want you to use our lamps, large language models for them because you won't be able to
understand anything otherwise.
In all, you have the freedom to adapt to your learning style.
So we're very heterogeneous in that sense.
In that sense, my advice is really focus on learning and scholarship and understanding.
Read another way.
Don't worry about the exam when you're in the lecture.
If all you're doing is worrying about the exam, you're not going to learn a whole lot.
Yes, you have an exam, unfortunately.
But if it were up to me, that exam wouldn't be there.
That would be replaced with something else.
It's there because it's there, you know.
OK, so we will enable you to learn and prepare you for the exam.
As I said, focus on understanding, learning and mastering the material in that sense.
Don't take the lectures that way.
Lectures are basics and they will actually they are, they have a lot of concepts connected to the
exam in the end.
But lectures are there to really enable all of these, I would say.
So lectures have a value that's much beyond the exam or the grade you will get in this course.
OK, so reinforced problem solving skills with homeworks.
And I already said this, and I should also say that most of you will pass this course.
This is not the worst weeder course in the freshman year.
Our pass rate is 8283%, maybe more.
So most of you don't need to worry about it.
Of course, if you're in the 16%, you may need to worry about it, but at least you will learn a lot,
right?
At least it's not 50% or 40%.
It's OK.
And we will release a lot of material to help you for the help you with the exam.
OK, we're going to see a lot of this.
So you can see from past lectures, these are Spring 2023 and Spring 2025 websites.
There are a lot of problem solving sessions and we keep adding them to this.
So summary, basically, learning is for life.
It never ends exam studies until you pass and it ends so the pain goes away after the exam.
But learning is an enjoyable process.
An exam could be an enjoyable process also if you have the right mindset.
So focus on learning and scholarship because that's what will matter in if.
I know it's easier to say, but 30 years down the road when you're doing something great.
Will ask you what, what grade did you get for course X?
It's good to have that perspective.
You know, I, I give that perspective to my graduate students also when they choose a research topic.
It's good to think about 30 years down the road, where will this idea be?
Where will this research be right?
You cannot of course predict the future easily, but you can.
This thought exercise is very useful in deciding what kind of things to research and what kind of
things to focus on.
OK so basically this is my summary.
Approach this course of the learning experience.
Develop your long term trade off analysis and critical thinking and decision making skills and while
doing so, find and choose the learning style that works best for you.
We have a lot of ways of attending lectures, as you have seen.
So what will we learn?
Well, we've already said this, but let's look at some more depth and why we care.
Hopefully we'll discuss why we care also.
So why do we have computers?
I think I've already said this.
Or why do we do computing?
In other words, we want to solve problems, right?
And we have a lot of problems we're going to see If you reword the sensor, maybe you don't solve the
complete problem.
You have a big problem in mind.
Computers can help you gain insight to solve this problem.
And this is what Richard Hamming had in mind.
How many people know about Richard Hamming?
Hamming quotes.
OK, error correcting quotes.
Yeah.
OK.
This coming from some lectures, probably.
And he basically said that computing is the goal of computing is to gain insight, not to crunch
numbers.
So you can think of this as machine learning, for example, today, it's crunching numbers, right?
It's crunching a lot of data.
It's doing a lot of matrix multiplications.
Matrix vector multiplications.
And the goal is to get the insight out of it.
So a good LLM will give you the insight in a correct way, robust way.
The crunching numbers is a means to an end, right?
OK, so why do we want this?
To enable a better life and future.
Hopefully any technology can be used for good or bad.
Hopefully we're on the good side here.
And morality is orthogonal to technology, unfortunately.
Now, OK, we're going back to the transformation arc.
How do we solve these problems?
And in modern technologies, we solve these problems by orchestrating electrons.
Essentially computers move electrons so that this problem is solved.
And we already said that solving the problems by electrons is not easy because we don't, we're not
able to currently communicate with the electrons.
We cannot say electron go from here to here and do this addition, right?
Or set of electrons.
So people have built this transformation hierarchy, which you have seen.
You've taken an algorithms course, right?
OK, so you know what an algorithm is and you implement that algorithm in some programming language.
And there are many, many programming languages and you execute that on some sort of system software
which interacts with the hardware with an interface.
And then there's the micro architecture that implements that interface.
We're going to see the distinction between especially the lower parts later on, which executes using
logic principles, logic gates, which are built on devices, which we're going to hopefully see
toward the later end of this course today.
And computer architecture, as I said, is the expanded view looks like this.
OK, so Richard Taming said this.
This is his, him and his cat.
So this is the hierarchy.
Again, I'm not going to go through this.
This is for your reference.
This is really what an algorithm is.
Hopefully everyone knows what an algorithm is.
I'm not going to test you on this, but this is for your reference.
This is a background algorithm needs to have specific properties like it should be finite, it should
be definite precise.
It's going to be, it should be effectively computable by the by the hardware and the language ISA.
I'm going to talk about that because you may not have seen it.
How many people have seen ISA before?
OK, some people, not a lot, not as many as algorithms.
So this is the contract between the software and the hardware.
What the programmer assumes hardware will satisfy and vice versa, meaning what the hardware will
promise will happen, right?
We're going to see this a lot.
Micro architecture is a specific implementation of the ISA itself.
Basically, we're going to see many, many micro architectures that are part of the same ISA.
For example, X86 ISA, We're going to see this.
There could be many implementations.
Intel has many implementations.
IMD has many implementations logic, essentially digital logic circuits are building blocks of the
micro architecture, for example, gates.
Hopefully by the end of today you'll see some example of gates and devices are actually physical
devices.
Transistors, for example, are devices on top of which logic gates are built and devices operate
based on principles of physics which govern the operation of electrons.
That actually completes the picture in the end.
So we're going to focus a lot on these three.
Parts in the first part of this first half of this course, actually most of this course I would say,
but we're going to touch upon the upper parts also impact, for example, effect of the design
decisions that you may do over here on the system software, the language, the compiler.
I didn't talk about compiler over here, but there's some some software, some piece of software that
takes the language the program is written in and that compiles it into the language that the
hardware understands, right?
That there's some step, a lot of these can be automated with LL Ms.
nicely today.
And in my opinion, at least, the language debugging, programming, compilation parts can be
relatively easily optimised and maybe done mostly by machines.
Not right now, today, it can be aided a lot, but maybe in a few years.
Of course, if you want to do, if you want to do something complex, for example, if you want to
design something over here and also something over here at the same time, that may not be that
easily done by the machines because the machine may not know well machine meaning the AI engine may
not actually know what's going to happen over here, right?
Because that could be something new.
OK, So what is computer architecture?
Let's do it a little bit.
Officially it is.
It is really the science and art of designing computing platforms.
And this is the broad definition.
Computing platform includes the interface between the hardware and the software, the hardware, the
system software, and the programming model.
And I say science and arts because it is science.
Clearly, we need to, we do engineering and we actually develop based on scientific method, things
that work.
But it's also hard because there are a lot of unknowns in the process because it interacts with the
humans, right?
For example, when you design A computing platform, you don't know what workload will be executed on
it because that computing platform will be used five years down the road.
Is that the bell?
That's a new bell, huh?
So why didn't it?
Why didn't it ring earlier?
OK, interesting.
Maybe you have a robustness problem with the bell.
As you can see, right, It didn't ring earlier.
So let me finish this slide and we're going to take a break.
Essentially, what is the goal of the design?
Our goal is to achieve a set of design goals.
This platform, we want to achieve a set of design goals.
What what are the goals?
So for example, a supercomputer may be designed to get the highest performance on Earth on workload
XYZ, let's say your favorite LLM large language model.
That's a very specific specialised supercomputer, right?
Or you may want the longest battery life at a form factor that fits in your pocket with cost less
than some amount.
Now you can see that multiple metrics came in, and there are multiple metrics even in the first one,
but that's not actually spelled out very well.
So this is more of a mobile system.
Or you want the best average performance across all known workloads or all workloads that you care
about catering to at the best performance and cost ratio.
This is more general purpose computing.
So super computing, mobile computing, general purpose computing with one single line liner if you
will, and there could be many other things.
Now, designing each of these is different from designing the other one, but fundamental principles
are all the same.
They're all built on transistors and they're all built on this transformation hierarchy.
It's just the design decisions of how you connect the components, what kind of architecture you
design, what kind of techniques you employ.
Those are the things that are different and that's what we're going to see in this course.
Like before we take a break, let me show you a couple of examples of this.
You can see these are computing machines.
This is a computing machine.
How many people know about this one?
Mr.
Bean, Is he still popular?
OK, I'm not that old.
OK, this is Mr.
Bean's self driving car in 1992.
Of course, he's pulling some things to make it self drive, right?
And then this is an old self driving car from 2008 or so.
You can see that there is a computing device that enables it to drive and modern self driving cars
are much better.
This is a data centre.
This is one of the supercomputers, Tianhe 2, I think from China, this is from Japan, Fukaku, You can
see that these are huge platforms and you have different design goals over here.
This is a systolic array machine learning accelerator that we're going to see.
We're going to see the fundamental principles of it in one of the lectures in the future.
I'm not going to talk about that right now, but Google has introduced it and many other companies
are building accelerators like this to accelerate machine learning.
These are very specialised machines, as we will see.
It's called TPU.
As you can see, there are many generations.
I cannot keep up with these generations, so I stopped at TP UV4.
I think they're at V6 right now.
This is Tesla self driving cars that are essentially also mostly machine learning accelerators that
are designed in a slightly different way.
And this is their chip.
Again, I'm not going to go through the details.
We're going to see some of the basic principles of it in systolic arrays later on and GP us and you
can see that the goal is to design.
They actually have training clusters that have these chips and many, many of these chips.
And this is this is one of my favorite pictures because they actually say that we're not designing
just a chip, we're not designing just a software.
We're designing everything across the stack, the chip, the system cluster software, and they
actually built compilers and the system software to make sure this is very efficient, etcetera.
Of course, improvements can be made.
This is a GPU.
These are more recent GPUs included also.
And you can see that it's not just a compute chip, but also interconnects over here.
Again, I will not go through the details of it.
We'll see interconnects later in the course.
And the reason people are building bigger and bigger of these things probably is AI, as you can see,
and you can put multiple GPUs together in different ways.
So these are different ways of interconnecting different chips, both compute chips and memories.
So you can see that interconnection technologies, how you connect components is actually also
important on how you partition a problem and communicate between different processors executing
different pieces of the problem.
So these are all fundamental, these are all computer architectures and the designs as you make
actually affect performance energy.
All of the metrics we talked about, this is a wafer scale chip.
It's like this big and people have designed this, Seribus has designed this so that they can
accelerate machine learning, lots of memory and lots of compute put together.
Again, this is not the biggest one.
The bigger one is I guess WSE 2/3, which is the process generation.
You can see that there are 4 trillion transistors on this thing.
You can, this is real.
This is a real picture.
The person is holding it.
Now imagine how to power up this thing, imagine how to make it robust, reduce it from faults,
etcetera, reduce to faults, etcetera.
And you can see that there's a lot of memory on top of this chip.
Not enough, not enough to do huge things, OK.
There are many, many other AI and ML chips that are being built also.
These are some different platforms for genomics that we do a lot of work on.
These are processing in memory platforms.
You can find this in our lab at ETC building.
This is a system where you have memory.
Inside the memory chip, you have computation.
This is something that we've been working on for 15 years or so.
And now it's it's happening.
We have these real systems.
We're going to talk about that later.
And many different companies are doing something of this sort.
This is actually what you can see in memory.
And inside the memory you have computation, OK.
There are many companies that are doing this will at some point talk about this.
And the goal is to again accelerate important applications because moving data from memory to the
processor consumes a lot of energy and performance.
OK, so I think I'm going to stop here because these are examples of how to do a hardware software
code design.
Now let's take a 1514 minute break, 1520.
That's a good round Number to come back at.
Let's see if the bell will ring 4 minutes after the bell, assuming it rings and assuming it rings on
time.
OK, cool.
I went over some of these slides relatively fast just to give you an idea of what's happening in
industry today.
So these are processing in memory chips, which is a fascinating idea.
Put the memory together with processing, or put processing inside the memory chip.
We're going to talk about that.
Usually these things are designed separately, but people are breaking that barrier today.
You can see that many different companies are building their own memory chips that can compute.
So remember the axiom?
We had this expanded view.
It's already happening.
Basically all of these systems that you have seen are really trying to design some hardware and
design the software on top of it together with the hardware and also all of the system stack so
they they can get better and better efficiency and performance.
So that way for scale system for example, it's designed to put a lot of memory and compute together.
There's some hardware design inside it, which we will cover in a later lecture, like SIMD
processing, vector processing, as you will see.
But there needs to be a lot of software components like compilers, programming models, programming
mechanisms such that the programmer can take advantage of the underlying hardware, trillions of
transistors such that they can actually make it work.
Make it work at high performance and also make it work in the sense that if one of these processing
elements fail, fails, how do you actually make sure that you don't get the wrong result?
So there are mechanisms inside that wafer scale chip that enable that.
OK, why do we study computer architecture?
I think some of this we already covered.
So I'll go through this relatively quickly.
This is actually a little bit more detailed description of what what computer architecture is.
Let me go over it.
It's a science and art of designing, selecting, and interconnecting hardware components and
designing the hardware software interface to create a computing system that meets functional
performance, energy consumption, cost, and other specific goals.
This is restricting itself to the hardware and the hardware software interface, a more traditional
definition, but we're taking a more broader approach.
So why do we want this?
We want to enable better systems.
We've already discussed enough of this, so I'm not going to harp on that more, but one thing I will
mention is a way of designing better system is looking at workloads.
So you want to actually customise to the workload.
That's the upper part of the hierarchy, problems, algorithms, right?
And then there's a lower part which is technology.
Technology also changes.
People actually develop new hardware.
And if you don't have a way of incorporating that into a processor, you may not be able to actually
take advantage of that new technology, new materials.
For example, if you come up with a new material that can move electrons much faster, then you can
actually like superconducting technologies.
If you can actually take advantage of superconducting technologies or quantum technologies to build
an architecture that can be much more efficient, much faster, much more parallel.
You can also enable better systems.
So I can exploit advanced and change the underlying technology and circuits.
You can enable new applications.
And I think I don't need to give you examples of this, especially with the AI generation today,
right?
These LLMS were not there if it weren't for the GPUs initially, more recently TPUS, etcetera.
But there are other applications like 3D visualisation, virtual reality, self driving cars.
All of these are enabled by better and better computing systems.
You can enable better solutions to problems and software innovation has built has been built on
these trends and changes in computer architecture and over many, many, many, many decades the
performance improvements of each generation of hardware has been 50% or more.
This is actually continuing with specialised architectures, with general purpose architectures.
It's very difficult to sustain this for reasons we will see later in this course, but enabling
better solutions come because of faster and better hardware also and also understand why computers
work the way do, which is going to be a core component of what we will study.
I should also say that today is a very exciting time to study this because this is at the core of
how you can actually innovate today, right?
And also industry as well as academia.
When I say industry, industry is important because academia is always ahead, right?
When we do research, we do research 10/15/20 years, sometimes 30 years down the road and we are
patient as academics.
We believe in what we do, and we show demonstrates using scientific method engineering.
Implementations, prototypes, that this is a good thing to do and industry at some point picks it up.
Some smart person in the industry says, oh this is great research, let me pick it up and it happens,
right?
Or you create a start up and you actually make it happen yourself.
So today actually industry is following some of this and there's a large paradigm shift to novel
architectures.
There are many different potential system designs possible.
Again, there's a laundry list, but there are many difficult problems motivating and caused by the
shift, like data intensive applications.
Power is a big issue today, Energy, thermal constraints, complexity of design.
As you will see, we will build increasingly complex microprocessors in this course.
Build meaning look at the design principles of that.
There are difficulties in technology scaling as we will see, meaning reducing the size of the
circuits, size of the transistor, memory bottleneck.
This is why people are putting memory and compute closer to each other so that they don't move the
data from a sensor to the storage device to main memory, to caches on the processor, to the
register file, and eventually compute units and back and forth and back and forth.
If you put processing next to the sensor or next to the storage or next to the memory, you can move
the data very little.
And Data moment actually consumes a lot of energy today, as we will also see, there are reliability
problems, there are programmability issues.
There are many, many issues, basically security issues.
For example, how do you actually do private computation on data that you don't want to expose to
someone?
You put your computation to the cloud, you don't want anyone to see it, and you want to actually
guarantee that no one sees it.
How do you actually guarantee that?
Very difficult to do.
And this is where actually privacy preserving technologies like homomorphic encryption comes in, but
they're actually very slow today.
So there are no clear definitive answers to these problems.
So computing landscape is very different from 10 to 20 years ago.
I've been studying computers since 1997 or so.
I don't consider what I studied in high school studying it was interesting, but I took a version of
this course in winter 1998 from who would become my PhD advisor, Professor Yale Pat.
And I was fascinated by how a computer works from the ground up before.
In high school, I programmed, for example.
Programming is interesting.
Yes, sure.
But you really don't know what's going on underneath, right?
I programmed in BASIC, for example.
How many program people program in BASIC?
Nobody These days, yes.
OK, maybe one a few people over here don't.
OK, we're not going to talk about your ages.
Yeah, but Basic is a fun language, no question about that.
But you don't understand what's going on.
When I took the course in winter 1998 at the University of Michigan for meal, Pat, who's actually
one of the authors of the book that you have, one of the books that you that I assigned for you,
it's actually, it becomes like the magic goes away, basically.
How does it work, Right.
But when I took it and when I did my PhD, computing landscape was very different.
There was no AI, basically.
I mean, there was AI, of course, but there was no hype or no big investment in AI because people
didn't believe in it, because sophisticated processes didn't exist at that time.
People were pushing for general purpose computation, for example.
But today everything is changing applications.
AI is one example.
I believe genomics is another example.
Technology is changing.
There's a lot of different technological changes, like how do you actually design memories that can
compute and also requirements.
So these three things are really important actually, if you want to have a paradigm change.
Sometimes the conditions need to be right, and in this case, applications are changing, technology
is changing, and requirements are changing.
Requirements are also very important.
Like people when they design computers in the 1950s, sixties, the biggest concerns were cost and
reliability and performance.
Usually performance was the most one, the most biggest one because they could solve the other issues
because they were designing supercomputers.
Overtime energy became a big concern.
Overtime power became a big concern.
Can we actually power these chips?
And more recently, right now, what's becoming a concern is sustainability.
And I think sustainability is going to be very important into the future.
So basically as these change, every component, its interfaces as well as entire system designs are
being re examined.
So you're at a point where people are re examining things.
That's why you see the wafer scale chip, right?
That thing appeared in 2019 or so, not before people had the idea, but nobody was brave enough to
actually design that wafer scale chip and put it as a commercial product.
OK, So this is an example system in your pocket.
We're going to see different components of it.
I've already said that I should also give you this story very quickly.
So we are taking this expanded view, but we're not taking sides on the top versus bottom.
It's good to mention this.
So there's top, you can have improvements on the top, right, which is algorithms, software,
etcetera.
There's bottom, you can have improvements on the bottom also like devices, how do you build better
devices that can do computation?
So there's this sometimes tension between the software and hardware, which I don't like to view of
view as tension.
It's more of a cooperation.
We want to actually build a better cooperation between them.
So this is Richard Feynman's.
There's plenty of room at the bottom.
He gave a lecture how many people know about Feynman?
OK, that's good.
Feynman's a famous physicist who who was very clear in how he explains concepts of physics.
And he gave this lecture saying that there's plenty of room at the bottom, meaning when people were
thinking, oh, technology is not going to improve that much, we're not going to build transistors
that are small, etcetera.
He said, don't worry, we're going to build a lot of things and as long as we envision and we try to
make it happen.
So these are some of the things that he envisioned, for example, possibility of direct manipulation
of individual atoms.
And this enabled a lot of thinking in nanotechnology.
For example, he was interested in denser computer circuitry, quantum computing, etcetera.
He was also interested in the swallowing.
The doctor basically have a circuit that you swallow and looks at whatever has happening in your
body, medicine, etcetera.
So I can keep reading about this, it's actually good to think about this.
But I still believe there's plenty of room at the bottom.
This is, we've got, we've come like 60 years after Feynman talked about this, 60 plus years.
And sometimes people keep saying, oh, technology will not improve.
We're not going to come up with a better underlying hardware.
I'm not going to necessarily call transistors, but underlying hardware.
They could be transistors.
As long as you push forward and you innovate, you question, you come up with new materials, new
techniques, you're going to come up with better hardware and that can unleash and enable new ways
of doing things.
We're still, for example, very far away from doing robotics.
That is very human like.
There's a lot of innovation that has happened, but some of the materials that we use that are
computing device are actually limiting us in terms of how we can do robotics in a very seamless,
flexible fashion that's integrated with the environment.
Like I'm very, I feel at least very integrated with my environment, right?
Hopefully you guys feel that way too.
But robots are not that way today.
Their materials are not, let's say that similar.
It's good to think about it.
OK?
There's also plenty of room at the top.
These folks have basically written a paper that kind of states the obvious, which is known by many
people.
But as it becomes difficult to do things with hardware because at some point you need to change the
paradigm in hardware so that you can do bigger things.
But sometimes there's some business as usual where you actually have the same hardware and with the
same hardware.
If you want to get bigger improvements, you need to focus on the algorithms.
In the end, I think both of these are true.
There's plenty of room both at the top and the bottom as long as you innovate, but much more so if
you can communicate well.
Between and optimise between the top and the bottom.
So design the software such that it takes advantage of the underlying capabilities of the hardware.
And vice versa, design the hardware such that it caters to the requirements of the software.
And this is happening to some degree today, but there's more to be done.
OK?
That's why we take the expanded view.
So I'm harping on this, but there's a good reason because sometimes people say, OK, software is more
important.
Hardware is more important in the end, they're both important.
OK, now this brings me to hardware versus software in a different way.
This course might seem like it's only computer hardware, but it's not only computer hardware.
It's actually how to design computers more than hardware or software.
It's more conceptual.
Meaning we, we design, we, we, we basically talk about, study the concepts of how to design
computers, right?
A lot of the things that we talk about are going to be done in hardware, but all of these concepts
are actually applicable to software.
So we're going to see, for example, pipelining software use that also the same concept in a
different way, out of order execution software use that also prefetching.
Every concept that we actually are going to touch can be done in software also.
So it's good to think about that.
And certainly the ideas are broader than hardware and software.
And I, I should say that you will be much more capable if you master both hardware and software and
the interface between them, because there are relatively small number of people who can do that.
A lot of people can program.
In fact, these days it's becoming a lot easier.
As we discussed earlier, you can develop much better software if you actually understand the
hardware.
You can design better hardware if you understand the software, and you can design A better system
which is not hardware or software, but both if you actually understand both in the end.
And that's what we.
We want to do, in the end, we design.
We want to design systems.
We don't want to just design software for existing hardware.
It's possible to do, but it's limited.
And vice versa.
We really want to design a system such that something happens that doesn't exist today.
OK, so we will cover the interface hardware, software interface and the micro architecture a lot.
And I've already said this, we'll focus on trade-offs and how they affect software a lot.
And we, for example, you call the example chips and platforms we surveyed relatively quickly.
We're going to go into more depth in some of these.
So we'll have Electron GPUs, for example, we'll have Electron systolic arrays.
We'll have many lectures on CPUs.
And these are examples.
Any questions?
Otherwise, I'll give you some more logistics, and then we'll start with transistors if time permits.
OK, let me give you some more logistics.
Some of you asked questions, and I want to get these out of the way.
We've already introduced ourselves.
There are also other people who are here.
Maybe they can raise their hands.
OK, You can see some of my PhD and master's students.
Suguras is here.
Maria is there.
Spiros is there.
Andreas who is there?
Harsh Harshita, did I miss anyone?
Oh, OK.
Irini is there also so you can see that we have a quiet international group of folks who are there
who are there to help you.
And they like sitting on that side for some reason, and that side is empty.
OK, So they're here to help you.
They're key assistants and guest lectures.
And as I said, we have a lot of student assistants who have taken this course, some of them multiple
times in the past.
I think Maria is a veteran.
For example, didn't she get the best TA award at some point?
Yeah, she got the best TA award at some point for the for TA ING this course.
Congratulations.
So you can take advantage of the fact that they have a lot of experience.
You can meet them at some lab assigned lab times.
These locations will be determined.
Labs do not start yet and if you need help, Moodle is a good place to ask your questions.
For technical questions, please send ask it on Moodle because a lot of people monitor Moodle.
If you send me e-mail, my e-mail is like a leaky bucket.
You get a lot of faults.
I may be able to see it, but sometimes I don't see it and I get a lot of e-mail unfortunately.
If you have a personal e-mail, definitely contact me and Mohammed and the head assistants, for
example, if you cannot come to an important lab, for example, if you're going to miss labs for some
reason, we need to handle that.
But if you have technical questions, this is the best place.
And there are office hours, and you can also write an e-mail.
I guess e-mail is also OK, but Moodle may be easier because Moodle automatically sends e-mail
anyway.
Is that correct?
OK, OK.
There are office hours and we'll provide these locations.
Doom links.
Our website is up.
You can find a lot of information including links to all of the previous incarnations of this
course.
And the one that's going to be the most similar is going to be Spring 2025, and we'll have a slide
on that also.
Essentially, this is your single point of access to all the resources as well as your e-mail.
We're going to send you more information about labs, etcetera, how to sign up soon.
So we have lectures.
There's no attendance taken.
It's for your benefit.
I would recommend attending so that you can learn and broaden your perspective, but I don't take
attendance.
Sometimes we may have guest lectures as you see over here, and you can attend at your convenience.
Also, lab sessions.
You should definitely attend the lab sessions.
And I think this date is correct, right?
March 3rd is when the labs will start.
OK, correct.
Mayank.
OK.
I don't I don't look at the right place because I was expecting someone over there and they're not
there.
OK, lab organization, you can choose your preferred group and again, these slides are online.
You can figure out how to do this.
You can choose your partner.
OK.
If you have questions, ask Mayank or Atabach and any of the other Tasmania.
And if you don't fill the form, we'll randomly assign you a partner.
We don't have enough FPGA boards to do the lab, so he cannot do it individually.
OK, any, anything to add here?
OK, so these will be available starting from tomorrow.
So if you go to the links and you don't find anything, wait until tomorrow.
OK, grades from previous years.
Again, there is a form that will be announced with Moodle.
You can choose one of these options over here and again, I'll let you read these.
You can use your grade from last year if you've taken it or if you want to improve it, you redo the
labs.
There's a final exam again, don't worry about it right now.
Don't worry about it during the lectures, but optional homeworks and solving past exams will
definitely be useful for final examination.
They'll be useful for reinforcing the concepts that we cover in lectures.
Anyways, so these are some reading assignments for this and next week.
So this I will give you a reading assignments.
You're welcome to do them and they will help you.
No question about that.
You don't have to do them, but they will definitely help you to reinforce the concepts because
clearly I cannot go into all the detail in the lectures.
I'll give you the basic concepts and the most important things.
But if you want to learn more, these two books are actually very useful.
And these are the chapters that are assigned initially.
We will have a lot of reading assignments in the first half of the course, and then we will have
almost no reading assignments from these books in the second-half of this course because these
books actually don't, in my opinion, cover what we intend to cover.
They're not up to date enough to cover things like systolic arrays, for example.
You will not find systolic arrays in this book.
You'll not find enough information about GPUs.
You'll not find enough information about memories, the most important things that are happening in
computer architecture or computing system design today.
But they're very good at the fundamentals that we will cover in the first half of the course.
How many people know binary numbers?
OK, That's why we don't teach them in this course anymore.
That's good.
If you don't know binary numbers, you can learn easily.
OK, these are the reading assignments.
Again, I'm going to skip this, but you can find these online.
And within two to three weeks, we will be done with a lot of chapters.
Actually, at least the lecture material will cover them.
And you're welcome to do these readings.
And you're, it's OK to get help from LLMS at your own risk, at your own risk is always a good thing
to think about.
We have an extra credit assignment.
Also, this is a research talk that I delivered a couple of years ago for 30 minutes.
And I'll give you a 1% extra credit.
LLM, no AI use permitted and you'll get a 0 if you use AI.
If you want to get a zero, you can use AI of course.
So it's permitted in that sense.
But if you want to get the extra credit, it's not permitted, let's say.
So basically, I would like you to watch this lecture and think about what are your key takeaways.
What did you learn?
What surprised you about the content?
What excited you?
What may be interesting?
What do you think the future solutions could be?
I'm not going to talk about this, but this is a phenomenon, multiple phenomena that we discovered in
my research group.
It's the fact that you can induce bit flips in DRAM chips.
It's called Row Hammer and I gave a talk about it 10 years after its publication, so I'll not spoil
the means so you can take a look at it.
OK, so future lectures and assignments.
You can also have a look at last year's website and plan for future lectures.
These are the links for your convenience.
Essentially, we're going to follow what we did in the past, but of course the content may change a
little bit and this is an example of last time prediction.
That's a concept that we will develop and examine in these lectures.
The microprocessors that you yous are all doing some sort of last time prediction.
That's a very basic prediction.
It's an example of speculative execution, meaning speculative execution means you speculate.
In other words, it's the concept of doing something before knowing that what you're doing is needed.
So you do something before knowing that it's needed.
For example, you take your umbrella before knowing that it's raining.
You anticipate that it's raining.
You predict that it's raining because last time you looked at the sky and it looked like this, it
rained.
So basically you're exercising speculative execution by participating in the action of taking the
umbrella based on the conditions that you see.
So again, similar things, similar concept were here in 2026, Other people were here in 2025, and I
was giving the same lecture.
And you go back to the 2025 website and you can see that similar things may happen.
You anticipate that similar things will happen, right?
That's last time prediction.
Existing machines do that.
And we're going to cover this key concept.
But as you can see, this key concept spans much beyond the design of microprocessors.
It's a very fundamental principle.
It's a fundamental principle of learning actually also if you think.
About reinforcement learning, it's kind of based on this predictability that happens, right?
Remember Yvonne Paulo and the dogs and the bell?
Whenever the bell rings, food comes and the dogs get used to it.
Last time, last time, last time, every time, and it becomes reinforced many times.
OK, so these are actually the older editions.
As you go back, you will see that maybe the predictability reduces.
It's good to think about it.
Any questions on logistics?
OK, none.
So now let's go into some fundamental material, very basic things.
To begin with, we're going to cover some fundamental concept.
Essentially, we need to understand the fundamentals to do better, right?
Our goal eventually is to do better because we can change the world only if you understand it well
enough.
And especially the basics, fundamentals, because fundamentals never change or they stay there
forever.
And if you understand the past and present dominant paradigms, and we're going to look at that,
we're going to look at their advances and shortcomings.
And there are things that remain fundamental across many, many generations.
It's good to identify these patterns.
And there are techniques that people have developed that are actually very useful for some of the
fundamental problems.
And these techniques appear many times and we're going to see some of those techniques.
So what's a computer?
That's a good thing to start with, basically, right?
This is von Neumann who and we're going to look at the von Neumann principles of design in lecture 9
or so.
There are three key components to computing, computation, communication and storage and memory.
You need to compute do addition, multiplication, etcetera.
You need to store data in some sort of storage.
You need to communicate data between processors and also memories.
So a computing system looks kind of like this.
And we'll cover all three components.
Actually, we'll especially focus on processing in the first part of the course.
We'll focus increasingly on memory and IO will be in a lot of things we cover because communication
is very fundamental whenever you do process data and also communicate with memory.
OK, so let me give you a lay of the land of what we will cover.
So we will start with transistors today and tomorrow.
Tomorrow we will cover combination logic design, circuits that can do computation but cannot
remember.
That sounds like a terrible thing, right?
And then we're going to add memory to it, sequential logic design.
And also we're going to cover hardware description languages, how to describe hardware.
Basically these are specialised languages to describe hardware.
And we're going to cover timing and verification, how to make the circuits work essentially so that
they don't produce wrong results because you didn't give it enough time or you didn't do enough
testing to verify it.
So these are the digital design parts of the course.
So and then we're going to go into architecture and talk more about the hardware software interface.
We can get two different kind of instructions and architectures.
We're going to talk about assembly programming, how to program using ones and zeros, and also how to
abstract them using a little bit more, let's say, human friendly things.
And then we'll kind of cover a lot of things in micro architecture.
I'm not going to go through every single things of it, every single thing that's written here, but
all of these concepts are essentially used in existing CP US, out of order execution, super
execution, branch prediction.
And we're going to talk about other paradigms that are actually used in different ways in different
specialised architectures, including GP US.
And then we will jump into memory.
And we're going to cover a lot of memory.
We're going to talk about memory, but we're not going to focus on it a lot in the first parts of the
course.
But in the latter part of the course, we're going to talk a lot about memory because this is
actually one of the major ball necks today in memory.
That's one of the reasons why memory prices are increasing, because existing workloads demand a lot
of memory to store data.
They also demand a lot of memory to actually do things with the data.
So today we can build processors very, very fast.
We cannot build memories very fast.
So if you want to actually move data, move a lot of data from the memory to the processor, you need
to design memories that are much more expensive, that are higher bandwidth essentially.
So that's one of the reasons why the cost of memory is increasing.
The other reason is demand is increasing and it's importance is huge today.
More than 60% of the cost of a data centre system today is memory.
OK, so memory is important, but we're still going to cover it later.
If you take the Advanced Computer Architecture course, you will see that we will start with memory
because that's the problem today and that's the problem to solve.
If you want to actually innovate, that's the Advanced Computer Architecture course.
But here we are.
Basics.
OK, these are some of the processing paradigms you will cover.
And again, all of.
Of these are used in existing systems today and you will learn hopefully all of these and these
actually I kind of have these pictures, but these paradigms pan across the stack.
They have programming languages associated with some of these paradigms and they actually design
logic so that they can and they they designed the entire stack to make it work.
GPUs, for example, GPUs have their own programming languages, own hardware design, own logic, type
of gates to do computation, and also all of the interface in between, right?
Systolic arrays are another example for that.
OK, so we're going to cover combination logic first, as I said.
So this is the plan for the rest of today and also tomorrow.
So we will learn the basic building blocks, transistors from transistors.
We're going to cover logic gates.
We're going to talk about Boolean algebra.
How many people learn about Boolean algebra?
OK, how many people did not learn about Boolean algebra?
OK, that's good or bad?
I don't know.
Usually most people know, so I'm going to go through it relatively quickly, but it's going to be
important to design circuits.
OK, I've already said this combination logic circuits, and we're going to use Boolean algebra to
represent and minimise logic circuits.
OK, Before I move on, let me say, let me give you the distinction between general purpose and
special purpose processing.
We're going to talk about general purpose processing.
These are flexible.
Ideally they can execute any program you throw at it.
They're easy to program and use.
Unfortunately, because they're so general, they don't provide the best performance and efficiency or
best of any metric, let's say.
And then there are very specialised processors that are designed for a particular application like
an LLM, a specific LLM for example.
They are very efficient and high performance in executing that application.
Unfortunately, they're usually difficult to program and use and they're inflexible.
They can execute a limited set of application, and the extreme K is only one application.
So existing machine learning accelerators are examples of special purpose machines.
For example, existing general purpose CPUs are examples of general purpose machines.
And this is a trade off.
Basically today people are designing all kinds of machines.
If you look at a system on a chip, there is a general purpose component in it, CPU, and then there
is AGPU in it, and then there are machine learning accelerators, and then there are video
accelerators, audio accelerators.
Today, basically we have a heterogeneous system on a chip that consists of general purpose versus
special purpose components.
We're going to see this picture again.
So this is my old, old school picture of a general purpose thing.
It's an adjustable wrench.
How many people used it at some point?
Do people still use it?
OK, you cannot have AI use it yet.
A robot, a robot will have trouble with this, by the way.
OK, so that's an adjustable wrench, general purpose, and these are special purpose wrenches.
General purpose is flexible.
It can work with any bolt, easy to use.
Unfortunately, if you use that, you'll figure out that it's not the best fit.
It doesn't give you the best results or efficiency, especially if you're a mechanic, right?
And sometimes you try to get it fit and it doesn't work right?
And then you give up and then you go to the store and get one that actually fits right.
And these are special purpose and you can see that it's efficient and high performance, but it only
works for the thing for the bolt that is designed to work with, right?
And it's usually difficult to use.
Now, especially if you don't get it to work, it's very difficult to use.
You need to find something else, right?
It's inflexible, right?
So this is my example.
This analogy spends to hardware and software LLMS are general popular LMS that are chained with
everything and the kitchen sink and they may not be very good at your task, which may actually be
getting a recommendation for what kind of drug you may want to use, especially if you're a doctor,
right?
For or give to a patient, right?
So training in a specialised manner helps.
And in my opinion, they're the same thing basically.
OK, modern general purpose processors, I already said this, but you essentially have a lot of
components.
If you look at this is Apple's M1 processor, you have a lot of GP, US performance course, high
performance, general purpose processors.
They have also efficiency course, lower performance or low energy general purpose processors, neural
engine, machine learning, accelerators and caches, etcetera.
So all of the processors look like that basically.
Again, I will not go through these in detail, but the key take away is today you're living in a
heterogeneous world.
When I when I was studying computer architecture in 19 nineties, 2000s, there was only CPU, that's
it, C1 CPU.
Fast forward to 2020, you have all kinds of components on the chip.
And this has been enabled by the ability to integrate lots of transistors.
And if you have lots of transistors, you can use them for different things.
So a chip is really eating other chips so that you can actually put a lot of different types of
processing.
Units and we're going to see a lot of these modern GPUs are also quite heterogeneous internally and
these are Fpgas.
This is the FPGA board that you're going to use to do your labs and these are some other modern
Fpgas, special purpose processors and these are machine learning X rators are also special purpose
processors and there are other machine learning accelerators like we have seen there are also.
So just to make sure that it's not only about machine learning, there are a lot of important
applications in the world.
I mentioned genomics.
There's also a video, for example, right now we're exercising YouTube a lot and there's a lot of
video encoding and decoding that's happening across the data centres.
And they're going through some of these specialised accelerators that are designed to efficiently
compress, decompress and stream video content because video has very special characteristics in
terms of compressibility.
Different frames, for example, that are streaming are very similar to each other.
And while the frames are coming, you can do compression and decompression and storage at the same
time so that you can minimise the amount of data that you're moving or streaming.
And people like Google, for example, have been designing video accelerators for this purpose.
And some of these accelerators are actually on your on, on something like this as a system on a
chip.
Well, not necessarily this type, but there could be similar types.
OK, So we're going to cover a lot of these microprocessors, Fpgas, ASICS.
What are the differences?
So microprocessors are general purpose, Fpgas are reconfigurable and you will figure that out very
quickly in the labs.
You can actually we're going to talk about that one in a lab lecture and you'll see that you can
reconfigure connections and can essentially implement different types of execution models on an
FPGA.
It's very flexible in that sense, but it's not very efficient.
And in ASICS you customise every single hardware piece for executing an application faster, ML or
video for example.
So because microprocessors are general purpose and easy programmable, you can write a Java programme
or Python And you can do it very fast.
With LMS you can do it even faster maybe if you know how to use an LMFPGAS take much longer usually
because as you will also see, ASICS usually take longer because you need to customise the design
performance.
Usually microprocessors are not that good because they're a general purpose.
Remember they're designed to provide the best average performance that cost many applications.
They don't claim to be the best in any application.
Right?
Fpgas can be good.
Depends.
So this is debatable actually.
But ASICS are usually very high performance Fpgas.
Depends on whether the application fits or not.
OK, So what is it good for?
Usually we use CP US to do anything.
You can do anything with them.
Fpgas are usually good for prototyping or acceleration of applications that fit, and ASICS are good
for maximum performance in general.
That's why they're very, very much used for machine learning acceleration today.
OK, I will not go through these in more detail.
You will see this, but essentially there, there are a lot of differences in terms of what kind of
languages we use.
You will see this especially when we talk about hardware description languages.
We needed, we need a language to describe the hardware because hardware has some characteristics
that need to be conveyed or described that really doesn't exist in general purpose programming
languages.
For example, the notion of a clock, as you will see, that's going to be fun to see.
OK, so in this course you're actually going to start with microprocessors, learning how these work.
And we're going to program Fpgas, meaning we're going to implement a small microprocessor on an
FPGA.
So you're going to get kind of kill two boards with one stone.
You're going to get both of those.
That's good.
Unfortunately, we don't have time to do ASICS, but you're going to learn a lot of principles of
ASICS, OK?
We're going to use the Verilog language.
OK, Let me take a look at time.
This seems like a perfect place to stop because we're going to start transistors and I don't think I
can give you the idea in one minute.
So I'm going to see you tomorrow.
Have a good rest of the day.